<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text"></title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://www.robertocano.es/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es" />
<updated>2015-05-01T21:23:49+02:00</updated>
<id>http://www.robertocano.es/</id>
<author>
  <name>Roberto Cano</name>
  <uri>http://www.robertocano.es/</uri>
  <email>roberto.cano@gmail.com</email>
</author>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[My own multilanguage Jekyll website (I)]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/multilanguage-jekyll-website_I/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/multilanguage-jekyll-website_I</id>
  <published>2015-04-17T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Roberto Cano</name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    <email>roberto.cano@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;h1 id=&quot;a-very-long-introduction&quot;&gt;A very long introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Jekyll is an open source program, written in Ruby by Tom Preston-Werner,
GitHub’s co-founder. Jekyll is a simple, blog-aware, static site generator for
personal, project, or organization sites. Instead of using databases, Jekyll takes
the content, renders Markdown or Textile and Liquid templates, and produces a
complete, static website ready to be served by Apache HTTP Server, Nginx or another
web server. Jekyll is the engine behind GitHub Pages, a GitHub feature that allows
users to host websites based on their GitHub repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;– &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jekyll_%28software%29&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that saved me a whole paragraph in this post! Couldn’t really find better words
to describe Jekyll. A really interesting and simple tool to build websites from mere
ASCII files. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Hey! Like HTML, PHP and Javascript!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, ok, you got me. Indeed, most of web technologies are based on &lt;em&gt;ASCII&lt;/em&gt; files, apart
from Databases for example. Anyway the beauty of Jekyll is that the ASCII files are
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; files that follow a minimal set of rules to format text. This rules are
such that the bare ASCII file, without the parsing, is still quite readable. It is
similar to &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help:Wiki_markup&quot;&gt;Wiki Markup&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll is great, easy to use, even a baby can set it up, it is fast, simple, and generates
custom static pages that can be trimmed down to a minimum if needed. Piece of cake!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as always that something related to the web comes into my hands, I found a big
issue: design. I may not be a good designer&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but I know how a good design looks like.
Most importantly, I know how I like my website. Thus the first thing I did was to try
to find a suitable design for my minimalistic idea of a blog. Googling around I
stumbled upon a very neat and pretty Jekyll design called &lt;a href=&quot;https://mmistakes.github.io/so-simple-theme/&quot;&gt;So Simple&lt;/a&gt; from desginer
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mademistakes.com/about/&quot;&gt;Michael Rose&lt;/a&gt;. I fell immediately in love with it and decided that it was going
to be the new Look&amp;amp;Feel for my site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;setting-up-your-first-jekyll-website&quot;&gt;Setting up your first Jekyll website&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let’s say you’ve found, like me, a neat, cool and usable theme for Jekyll&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and you
want to start using it. The first thing you need to do is install Jekyll itself. You can
do that by opening a shell and executing the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;gem install bundler  &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# This install the bundler utility that eases dependency solving for Ruby&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git clone git@github.com:mmistakes/so-simple-theme.git &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# For the So Simple theme using SSH&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd &lt;/span&gt;so-simple-theme
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;bundle install &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# To install the Ruby dependencies specified in the Gemfile file. You may need sudo here.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;bundle &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;exec &lt;/span&gt;jekyll serve  &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# To serve the website at http://localhost:4000&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done! You have your new website up and running in your machine! Go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;http://localhost:4000&lt;/a&gt;
and check it out. Neat, right!? Well, true, nobody can see your website right now, but you do. Play around
and check all the nice things that come with the theme you’ve selected. If you need to stop the server just go
to the shell and Ctrl-C it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What hellish jargon is all this &lt;strong&gt;shell&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;sudo&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;website&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;jargon&lt;/strong&gt;??&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, wait. I didn’t disclaim that. Let’s do it now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;DISCLAIMER&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog is mainly aimed to advanced users and/or/xor developers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;with broad experience in Linux-ish systems that have been able to&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;solve the conundrums of the shell and have suffered early installations&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;of Linux distros in their flesh. I deny all liability related to a&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;misunderstanding and/or misuse of the instructions contained in this post.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: left&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Besides: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel better now. Let’s continue. Now that we have a theme on our hands that we can serve
from our own machine, what next? Well, it will depend on your theme of choice, but typically
the first thing you want is to edit the _config.yml file. This file contains the Jekyll site
configuartion. Things like the Blog’s name, server URL where the site will be hosted, type of
Markdown languge and other goodies are found here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then you typically have the _posts directory. This one contains the posts for your blog.
Inside this directory you may find some more directories: these are the categories of
your posts. And then inside the posts themselves. There are other interesting directories
at the root level:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_layouts - Containing HTML files with the layout of your different pages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_includes - Containing some more HTML files that are directly included in other HTML files (things like headers and footers)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;_data - Containing some valuable YAML data that can be used in your site to customize stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this files, and templates, and layouts, and YAML data are mixed and shaked together and then
compiled into your final site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the website you’ve downloaded, read the instructions and play around with it. You can always
build and serve the pages locally before you publish them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In follow-up posts I will explain how to add multi-language features to your site, how to publish it
in GitHub pages, how to add a custom domain and how to cook the best beef stew&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Hint: I’m not. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you intend to setup a Jekyll site from scratch please follow this &lt;a href=&quot;http://jekyllrb.com/docs/quickstart/&quot;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Don’t expect everything I say to be true &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/multilanguage-jekyll-website_I/&quot;&gt;My own multilanguage Jekyll website (I)&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 17, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[GitHub pages first contact]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/github-pages-first-contact/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/github-pages-first-contact</id>
  <published>2015-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2015-04-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Roberto Cano</name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    <email>roberto.cano@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Blogs and blogging is basically what is all about lately in the web. I’ve found that even certain news
media try to convey a sense of proximity with the reader by using a more personal and blog-like approach.
Nowadays it is important to have an on-line presence in places like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.twitter.com&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linkedin.com&quot;&gt;Linkedin&lt;/a&gt;,
and if you are a developer it is equally important to be present in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.github.com&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stackoverflow.com&quot;&gt;Stack Overflow&lt;/a&gt; for
example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to complement this is of course to have your own personal blog where you may have a more intimate
space where to publish more concrete and developed ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always had my own blog or website where I’ve been dumping this and that (mainly that…) as a form of
self-expression and mainly as a way of tracking the things that I’ve been doing over time. Sometimes memory
is ephemeral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without knowing about the existence of my personal blog a esteemed friend of mine was recently sharing
with me that he was starting a new blog &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.enriquerecarte.com&quot;&gt;Enrique Recarte Blog&lt;/a&gt;. He is an acomplished developer and architect
now tasting the goodies and baddies of London’s busy life. Our conversation was quite interesting and he introduced
me to the unknown-until-then GitHub pages service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been often paying for hosting services to host my website, and although it is usually not expensive,
it is always overpaid for the use I make of it. Besides it always brings a little bit of overengineering as I
tend to use CMSs (Content Management Systems) like Joomla or more recently WordPress. Although these two
products are great and have a big and active community around it, it is like using sledgehammers to crack nuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I really welcomed it when my friend Enrique was explaining to me how to prepare a GitHub pages site using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jekyllrb.com&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt;,
how it is automatically compiled when uploaded, and how to associate an already owned domain name to it through
the CNAME file. I should not go into much detail in this post as I’m preparing a more technical post about
Jekyll and all the steps I’ve followed to bring my site live, but it has been a really pleasant experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two things I love about Jekyll and the GitHub pages approach. First, that the source pages follow the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&quot;&gt;MarkDown&lt;/a&gt; format that will allow me to port my site to any future technology as it is just plain ASCII
with some extra headers for the FrontMatter engine. And second that the final website is just a static website
that will work on any webserver of the world. No need for PHP, databases or &lt;em&gt;fancy&lt;/em&gt; stuff. Yeah, ok, I know,
“how fancy a database is nowadays” you may say. However I prefer it this way. It is fast, easy to serve and I
can have a better control of the weight of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a follow-up post I shall explain how to set up your own Jekyll website with multilanguage and a search engine.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/github-pages-first-contact/&quot;&gt;GitHub pages first contact&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 10, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[En la panza del Mekaro]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/en-la-panza-del-mekaro/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/en-la-panza-del-mekaro</id>
  <published>2014-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-02-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Amaneció sentado, apoyado contra la mugrienta pared de un viejo y sucio
refugio. El húmedo aroma a cloaca trepaba por las paredes y escapaba por un
pequeño orificio horadado a ras de techo. A través del agujero se intuían a lo
lejos los primeros despuntes del amanecer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En la pared opuesta un sinfín de tuberías tejían un burdo entramado que
resonaba a intervalos regulares y dejaba escapar por los recodos un continuo
rocío de agua. Las gotas resbalaban suavemente por la pared y bañaban los
adoquines que adornaban la mayor parte del suelo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gabriell se levantó y sintió como su cuerpo entumecido chirriaba y crujía a
medida que se incorporaba. ¿Cuánto tiempo habría estado en aquel lugar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lo último que recordaba era aquel viejo buslizador hiperbárico y su insistente
vaivén a 5 por 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De repente, mientras se encontraba sumergido en su memoria a corto plazo,
Gabriell se dio cuenta de un pequeño detalle que había pasado por alto. Se le
heló la sangre de inmediato: aquel lugar no tenía puerta alguna de entrada.
Observó con detenimiento la estancia: el enjambre de tuberías de la pared
opuesta, el suelo salpicado de adoquines, la pared en la que había estado
apoyado quien sabe cuantas horas, la insulsa pared de su derecha y el tragaluz
que coronaba la pared de la izquierda, tan pequeño que solo un globerg podría
entrar a través de el. Pero ningún signo de algo que se pareciera ni
remotamente a una puerta o trampilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gabriell decidió cerrar los ojos y concentrarse en los sonidos que emanaban de
aquel calabozo y en los que se deslizaban sutilmente por la única conexión con
el exterior: gorgoteos, reflujos de agua, algún chirrido metálico espontáneo
proveniente de la red de tuberías, su respiración un tanto agitada y el latir
de su corazón. Más allá de aquella habitación no parecía haber nada más. Quizás
se encontrara en medio de un desierto, en una llanura infinita sin signos de
vida. Quizás estaba en un pueblo abandonado, campamento de muchos de los grupos
rebeldes que eran expulsados de la Unión.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No sabía dónde estaba, cómo había llegado allí ni como salir de aquel inmundo
sitio. Sin embargo Gabriell no perdió la calma. Si alguien le había encerrado
allí y no le había matado aún, era porque le necesitaban vivo y, de un momento
a otro, le harían saber porqué.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuará…(o no)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/en-la-panza-del-mekaro/&quot;&gt;En la panza del Mekaro&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 02, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lucky Lindy and the biggest hop of all]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/lucky-lindy-and-the-biggest-hop-of-all/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/lucky-lindy-and-the-biggest-hop-of-all</id>
  <published>2014-01-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-01-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Hi, dear old friend. Long time no see (again). This time, as always, because my
daily duties took over my online presence and didn’t have time to update my
personal diary. It is, however, more than OK, as it has been one of the most
productive periods of the last years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where should I start? Well, after I stopped writing, just after my Japan trip
(which was amazing!) I’ve been extremely busy…having fun! The summer in
Holland was unusually good, temperature around 22 degrees, almost no rain at all
and sun everywhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t resist to such weather and I was just jumping from party to party.
Spending all evenings (from Monday to Sunday) in places like the Roest,
Brouwerij Het Ij, Hanekes Boom, Vondelpark, Amsterdamse Bos. And by the end of
the summer 2 of the most amazing events of all summer: the Bloemendal 80s, 90s
and 2000s party and the Edelweiss festival. They were both magic and revealing.
I really enjoyed them. I love to dance, and I didn’t stop dancing. Mainly in the
Bloemendal one. And the DJ was incredibly good!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that party of course meant that I didn’t go to the gym for months! I think
I’ve lost every muscle I had build, but it was more than worth it. Now I should
come back…when I have time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the summer the routine tried to break through and settle in my life again.
I could not help but look for new activities to keep my mind in that thrilling
state. So I started my guitar lessons. Guitar-singing lessons. I found a
professional guitarist and singer, Joep Berkenbosch, which does exactly what I
wanted to do: play guitar finger-style and sing at the same time, ala
songwriter. So I started and we connected immediately. He’s really good
guitarist and singer, but he’s also really good teacher, which sometimes does
not have to be true at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been basically learning songs like Bob Marley’s Waiting in vain, Ben E.
King’s Stand by me or Beatles’s Here comes the sun. All of them beautiful songs,
with brand new chords I never played before and a special need for being able to
play the correct rhythm and sing at the same time. Now I’m just planing on going
wild….sorry live and play some songs in a public place, most likely with my
flatmate, who is an awesome singer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, while trying to get my obsession for the gym back I stamped on the most
exciting and awesome dancing lessons I’ve ever had: Lindyhop!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lindyhop is a dance for swing music from the 20s and 30s. It is fresh, funny,
relaxed and quite entertaining. The name of the dance comes (supposedly) from
Charles Lindbergh famous Atlantic hop with his plane, the “Lucky Lindy”. On the
newspaper the headlines read things like “Lindy hops the Atlantic” and from
there, as the dance was becoming popular, adopted the name Lindyhop. I believe
not only the dance is really engaging, but the particular lessons I’m taking
here in Amsterdam. The school is called Lindyspirit and the teachers, Quinten
and Sarah, are really good at getting you into the Lindyhop during the whole
lesson. I’m attending now to the second block, 8-count moves, and still love it
every time I go. I think it is the first time I go to a course and I forget
completely I’m trying to learn something, and just enjoy it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last, but not least, as usual, this is starting to be a year with a lot of
plans and trips! Next stop, Japan again, specifically Kioto, during the Sakura
(Cherry Blossom) and with one of my best friends. The plan: playing some songs
to the locals in the bar of a friend of my friend, while enjoying the sushi and
the doriyakis! If everything goes well, this will be the first time I bring my
guitar on a trip. I’m quite excited!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on the long term, the low humming of the stick to the Thailand plan…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope it does not take me that long to update this blog next time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(hint: also, in the meantime, I’ve started to learn calligraphy….why not!)&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/lucky-lindy-and-the-biggest-hop-of-all/&quot;&gt;Lucky Lindy and the biggest hop of all&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on January 19, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bootstrapping my friend]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/bootstrapping-my-friend/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/bootstrapping-my-friend</id>
  <published>2013-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2013-05-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Het is lang geleden! It’s been a while since I don’t write here and the reason
is…vacation! I’ve been traveling around the world (almost literally as I’ve
been enjoying of Cambodia and Japan in less than a month) and I’ve
been successfully disconnected of my everyday routine. Now that I’m back I’m
really struggling to get back at work and my OpenGL learning, but as a
compensation I’ve been toying around with several ideas that I was curious
about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On one hand I’ve been investigating about implementing Wireshark plugins
through its Lua interface to help analyse DVB Simulcrypt traffic captures,
which is quite useful in my job. This I did while helping in the integration of
our systems with one of our customers, and it proved to be extremely helpful.
The Lua interface for Wireshark is actually not really intuitive, and I needed
some examples developed by another colleagues to get a grasp on it, but I
finally I came up with a clean and easily extensible architecture that will
allow me to add more plugins in the future. If I have enough time I’ll post some
information on how this works to add my personal bit to the scarce information
that you can Google around about the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the other hand I’ve also had a grasp on FFMPEG filters as a consequence
of some POC needed for our research about video. In this case I basically
took the &lt;em&gt;drawtext&lt;/em&gt; filter and I stripped it out of all the unneeded code until
I had a minimum plugin that I could easily tweak to add, for example, noise to
the video. Actually there exists a plugin that achieves the same, but this was
just to have a placeholder in case I need to add some custom filters. In this
case it wasn’t that difficult as in the Wireshark’s plugins case, but still the
information I could find googling was not enough and outdated in some cases.
However I also found this quite interesting and useful for some quick proof of
concepts as you have all the decoding/encoding power of FFMPEG but you can
easily implement a &lt;em&gt;man in the middle&lt;/em&gt; attack!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;On the third hand…yes, whatever! I’ve also been having a look to Twitter’s
Bootstrap to use it as a web interface to control some of our systems. I
friend of mine who has been a web developer for Hyves (the Dutch Facebook)
recommended this to me as an accesible set of web widgets. Basically I didn’t
want to care too much about the look and feel. While learning it I found quite
interesting the fact that it is done merely with CSS and JavaScript, which
allows for an embedded system to have quite a lightweight web server as there is
no need for any server side support, like PHP. I immediately felt in love with
Bootstrap because of this but, as always, I had problems to set up the first
mockup of my project. Luckily I found a beta project called
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.divshot.com/&quot;&gt;Divshot&lt;/a&gt; that offers an online WYSIWYG tool to compose
websites using Bootstrap. As opposed to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jetstrap.com/&quot;&gt;Jetstrap&lt;/a&gt;,
Divshot is still in beta stage and you don’t have to pay for it (although
Jetstrap allows you to create one website for free, I liked Divshot more). So I
created my stepping stone through Divshot, got the result and then customised
it manually to my needs. The result is actually pretty cool and I’m really happy
with it. Let’s Bootstrap!!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last thing I’ve learned on this road trip is about WebSockets. I was
completely convinced that WebSockets were just plain TCP sockets brought to the
browser, but they are actually quite different, and although based on TCP
sockets (of course!) they add an extra layer that you must comply with. So in
the end to implement a server that provides data to a web interface, you need to
actually implement a WebSocket server, which is something I don’t like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it’s been a cool trip and now I continue designing my web interface and
trying to add some cool animations to it. Later on I’ll ask for the advise of my
Hyves friend as he’s an expert in usability and design, to let him criticise my
first web development attempt!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, I hope, more on my OpenGL development adventure!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/bootstrapping-my-friend/&quot;&gt;Bootstrapping my friend&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on May 12, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenGL RedBook 7th edition and the price to pay]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/opengl-redbook-7th-edition-and-the-price-to-pay/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/opengl-redbook-7th-edition-and-the-price-to-pay</id>
  <published>2013-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;In the last days I’ve formed my own opinion regarding the seventh edition of the
OpenGL standard, by the Khronos group. I’ve been reading the first chapters of
the book, consuming every word and trying to put in practice every example, to
get a grip on the not-so-new OpenGL 3.3.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I lost my touch with technology, and that maybe I was too far away
from the topic that I couldn’t event get a basic understanding of the API.
However I did realize that 80% of the functions were deprecated (I remembered
this after a hundred pages reading…). Then I started wondering myself whether
the book was going to be able to teach me practical OpenGL. It proved
impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digging into google pool of wisdom to know more about this problem I found two
things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Everybody agree that the 7th edition of the OpenGL Red Book is good for
reference, but not for learning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Several of them pointed out this
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arcsynthesis.org/gltut/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this I learned 2 things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To read more carefully all the reviews of a book before blindly buying it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That, sometimes, free books are plenty of times better than pay-per-read
ones&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mentioned website is one of the best book/tutorial about something that I’ve
ever seen. Quite comprehensive, easy to follow, with up-to-date examples and an
easy reading, it is now my north star of the OpenGL books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are willing to learn modern OpenGL you must definitely try it. Then, when
the basic concepts sick, you can go through the OpenGL Bible (beware the 5th
edition as it is not as good the previous ones)  or the GLSL Cookbook than can
complement this basic knowledge with more advance techniques. But first is
first!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope to have saved you some time!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/opengl-redbook-7th-edition-and-the-price-to-pay/&quot;&gt;OpenGL RedBook 7th edition and the price to pay&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on March 11, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Camera movement and premature optimization]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/camera-movement-and-premature-optimization/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/camera-movement-and-premature-optimization</id>
  <published>2013-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-03-11T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;While writing the first bits and bytes of my ‘I-want-to-learn-OpenGL’ engine I
stamped myself against the camera implementation. As a first approach I was
trying to implement one of those fancy FPS walking cameras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently using the &lt;a href=&quot;http://glm.g-truc.net/&quot;&gt;GLM Library&lt;/a&gt;, which tries to
add back all the functionality present in previous versions of OpenGL and GLUT
to the new GLSL pipeline. Things like rotations, translation, perspective and
orthogonal projections are available in the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When thinking about how to implement the camera movement, my first approach was
to use a look_at vector that would serve both as the direction of the camera (so
the view vector) and the direction of the movement when using the forward key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also the control through the mouse would use the typical YAW, PITCH and ROLL
concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time I was presented to the Gimbal Lock concept that I will try to
tackle, both in code and blog, in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I ran into a problem. If I wanted the camera to move realistically,
every time the forward key was pressed I should move the camera in the direction
of the look_at vector. This meant updating the camera accordingly applying the
Yaw, Pitch, Roll rotation to the look_at vector before using that vector to
move forward. So I did so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result: I lost almost a 30% of performance just by calculating the rotation
every time!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not surprised by the lost of performance, but I couldn’t believe
professional applications were spending a 30% of the time in calculating camera
rotations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I decided to cheat a little bit on the user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we are going to update the screen around 60 times per second, and the user
cannot see the intermediate movements (only the final one), I don’t update
the look_at vector until the time for the rendering is due. Then I apply the
rotation to the look_at vector and I apply the movement according to that
vector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not exactly accurate, but it works. To understand why it is not accurate
think about the following scenario:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The user faces the north&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then turns the camera 90 degrees left, to the west, and moves 10 units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Then quickly turns the camera 180 degrees to the right, facing east, and
moves 10 units&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finally turns 90 degrees left, facing north again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Net result: no movement at all when the frame is rendered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Result with my fake implementation: 20 units of movement towards the
north!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However is hardly noticeable, and it saves a lot of time. Maybe when I can
use Quaternions it could become more realistic…who knows!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/camera-movement-and-premature-optimization/&quot;&gt;Camera movement and premature optimization&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on March 11, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[CSS, Blogger and Simple template transparency]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/css-blogger-and-simple-template-transparency/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/css-blogger-and-simple-template-transparency</id>
  <published>2013-02-25T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-02-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;It may seem quite obvious for any HTML/CSS developer how to do this, 
but I struggled for 2 hours to find out how to set a semi-transparent 
background while using the Simple template of Blogger. Usually websites
indicate how to do it while using the Dynamic template. My main problem
was to know how the pane component was called internally. Finally I could
find the solution in this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bloggeries.com/forum/showthread.php?t=26163&quot;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt;
from Bloggeries(http://www.bloggeries.com/).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must go to your Blogger configuration and click on &lt;strong&gt;Template&lt;/strong&gt;.
Then click on &lt;strong&gt;Customize. **This will bring the template customization page.
Click then in **Advance&lt;/strong&gt;, go to the bottom of the new categories pane and
click on &lt;strong&gt;Add CSS&lt;/strong&gt;. Here you can add the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot; data-lang=&quot;css&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;rgba&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;.7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Change the &lt;strong&gt;255&lt;/strong&gt; values to the RGB values you want for the background and
the &lt;strong&gt;0.7&lt;/strong&gt; to the alpha setting you prefer (from &lt;strong&gt;0.0&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;1.0&lt;/strong&gt;). Click
on &lt;strong&gt;Apply to Blog&lt;/strong&gt; at the upper right corner and enjoy the benefits of alpha
blending in your blog!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember this is valid for the &lt;strong&gt;Simple Template&lt;/strong&gt; of Blogger. I didn’t try
with other templates.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/css-blogger-and-simple-template-transparency/&quot;&gt;CSS, Blogger and Simple template transparency&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 25, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[PlayStation 4 and the future of videogames]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/playstation-4-and-the-future-of-videogames/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/playstation-4-and-the-future-of-videogames</id>
  <published>2013-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;This week Sony presented the next generation of PlayStation videoconsoles.
While not unveiling the physical device as such, some specs are known.
It is an AMD based machine, bundled with one of the so famous ATI Radeon
graphic cards. An increase of memory, form 512MB to 8GB will easy the data
transaction of the new generation of entertainment devices, being this memory
of the GDDR5 type.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazing?? No, not really. Nothing that a rather not-so-much bunch of bucks
cannot buy in the high-end PC market. However it is not the machine itself what
attracted my attention to the so expected Sony’s new videoconsole: it was the
technical demos and in-progress videogames I could see during the online
presentation. Not because these reflect what is coming with the PS4, but
because they reflect what is coming in the upcoming years for us, the gamers –
the hardcore gamers – and it is absolutely delicious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the tech demo from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.quanticdream.com/&quot;&gt;Quantic Dream&lt;/a&gt;
showing off the level of quality for character acting. For the first time,
I was almost convinced about the humanity of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MUMOHSL53L8&quot;&gt;old man&lt;/a&gt;
appearing on the screen. It is not that we’ve reached the singularity already
– not yet – but we are quite closer now. Looking to the eyes of the character
you could almost feel his soul, and that’s quite of an experience. It could be,
of course, that all the horsepower of the PS4 was put to work to achieve only
that moving head, and that for real production videogames that’s not going to
be the true experience, but I was glad to see that we are getting there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, the tech demo from the Unreal team and its &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unrealengine.com/&quot;&gt;Unreal Engine 4&lt;/a&gt;.
While still a little bit away form photorealism and with some minor issues I
could notice (like some unwanted aliasing in some geometry), the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_o7EsSfOFAQ&quot;&gt;demo&lt;/a&gt;
has such a quality that it could perfectly be just a trailer for an upcoming
movie in theaters next month. It is quite impressive, as this is, in my opinion,
just the tip of the iceberg. I noticed plenty of particle management – ice,
fire, smoke… – and also several film techniques applied to the &lt;em&gt;filming&lt;/em&gt; of the scene.
It looks as if you had only to watch at the screen, as it really looks like a
movie, and not like a game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last, but not least, games like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IuRwp6aCWRw&quot;&gt;Kill Zone 4&lt;/a&gt;
with an incredible ala Blade Runner-like city, unbelievable reflections and curved surfaces
that made the city real and alive. Also master-pieces – if they are not, they will be –
like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1WUSv5Ugm9c&quot;&gt;Watch Dogs&lt;/a&gt;, which shows that
not only awesome graphics are needed to grab the gamer’s attention, but a good
dosis of freedom, simulation and AI realism. In this game the gameplay seems
unbounded, unlimited and neverending. It is not the most impressive piece of code
regarding the graphics area that I’ve seen, but it feels like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Kq5KWLqUewc&quot;&gt;Deus Ex: Human Revolution&lt;/a&gt; to the
power of ten in the gameplay area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now what? It is obvious: to wait for the counterpart of Sony’s baby, the XBox 720 –
or whatever Microsoft wants to call it –. Sincerely I expect Microsoft’s proposal
to be even better than PS4. This way we, the gamers, will win a handful of
ever-lasting experiences in our minds and our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep on playing!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/playstation-4-and-the-future-of-videogames/&quot;&gt;PlayStation 4 and the future of videogames&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 24, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSX and OpenGL 3.2]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/osx-and-opengl-3-2/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/osx-and-opengl-3-2</id>
  <published>2013-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Roberto Cano</name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    <email>roberto.cano@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve bought the famous Red Book for OpenGL. This is the 7th
edition (so OpenGL 3.3). I bought this one because OSX Mountain Lion only
supports OpenGL 3.2 (by now) and I didn’t want to experiment the
frustration of trying to setup an example that finally I couldn’t run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway the experience is starting to be quite a nightmare. It turns out that
the resources available on the internet to setup an OpenGL 3.2 example under
OSX Lion using C++ are scarce. Most of them focus on bringing OpenGL 3.2
rendering context using Cocoa and ObjectiveC. While good enough for a bit of
testing, it is not what I wanted to start playing around with OpenGL. I needed
either C or C++, and even though I saw some examples of how to setup an
ObjectiveC/C++ binding, I didn’t want to spend time on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally it turned out that the solution was named &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glfw.org/&quot;&gt;GLFW&lt;/a&gt;
GLFW is the replacement
of GLUT (the GL Utility Toolkit) that was famous a long time ago. Now GLUT is
still available but it looks like it doesn’t support window hints for
OpenGL context creation, which is what is needed to create OpenGL 3.2 contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found really nice examples at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opengl-tutorials.org/&quot;&gt;www.opengl-tutorials.org&lt;/a&gt;. They setup the
OpenGL context using GLFW and GLEW. &lt;a href=&quot;http://glew.sourceforge.net/&amp;quot;&quot;&gt;GLEW&lt;/a&gt;
is the GL Extension Wrangler, a helper library to
determine which OpenGL extensions are available in run-time. With this two
libraries OpenGL 3.2 context creation is a piece of cake. First include GLEW
and GLFW. You must do this in that order as GLEW will complain if &lt;em&gt;gl.h&lt;/em&gt; is
already included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c&quot; data-lang=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Include GLEW&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;GL/glew.h&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// Include GLFW&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;cp&quot;&gt;#include &amp;lt;GL/glfw.h&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it’s time to initialise GLFW and set the hints for the window so the
created OpenGL context is 3.2:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c&quot; data-lang=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;glfwInit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;glfwOpenWindowHint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GLFW_OPENGL_VERSION_MAJOR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;glfwOpenWindowHint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GLFW_OPENGL_VERSION_MINOR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;glfwOpenWindowHint&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GLFW_OPENGL_PROFILE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GLFW_OPENGL_CORE_PROFILE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this a GLFW window can be opened with a OpenGL 3.2 context associated to
it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c&quot; data-lang=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;glfwOpenWindow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1024&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;768&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;32&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;GLFW_WINDOW&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last step is to initialise GLEW to be able to use the core profile of
OpenGL 3.2. To do this, the experimental mode of GLEW must be activated:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-c&quot; data-lang=&quot;c&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;glewExperimental&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;true&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;glewInit&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There we go. With this an OpenGL 3.2 context is created and we are ready to
issue OpenGL commands. Remember that OpenGL 3.2 is quite different to OpenGL
2.1, like for example no more glBegin()/glEnd commands are used to render
geometry. Instead use VBO (vertex buffer objects) to do it so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing to remember is that you must link against GLFW and GLEW, as well
as against OpenGL. In Mac OS X this is  achieved by adding the following flags
while linking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-bash&quot; data-lang=&quot;bash&quot;&gt;-lglfw -lglew -framework OpenGL&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy OpenGL coding!!&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/osx-and-opengl-3-2/&quot;&gt;OSX and OpenGL 3.2&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 24, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenGL 3.2: shaders everywhere!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/opengl-3-2-shaders-everywhere/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/opengl-3-2-shaders-everywhere</id>
  <published>2013-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2013-02-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Now that I’m getting involved into OpenGL 3.2 I realize how different it is
from OpenGL 1.2 (the last one I learned long time ago). No more glBegin/glEnd
blocks and only VAOs (vertex array objects) and  VBOs (vertex buffer objects),
shaders and basically server side structures and processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today while trying out some demos and writing some example code to understand
better how all this new structures are working together I found out that I
really need a deep understanding of GLSL (GL Shading Language) to be able to do
some cool things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After managing to create a color cube using VBOs, I fancy trying to outline the
3D geometry as I thought it could look cool. However, I struggled doing it as
the only feasible way, as far as I could understand, is by using shaders. As
currently my knowledge of shaders is rather low, I couldn’t find a way to
create the outline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyhow I feel it is a quite powerful tool to generate really nice effects, but
I;ll have to wait until I’m confident with the basics of OpenGL 3.2 to be
prepared to tackle GLSL and understand its deepness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I found about OpenGL3.2 is that it eliminated the fixed pipeline
by which OpenGL pre 3.1 renderered the primitives (applying transformations,
rotation, scaling, MVP matrices, etc,,,) and now it is all done through
shaders. So the next demos I intended to do with VBOs and VAOs is not working
just because I need a simple shader to be incorporated to the rendering of the
scene!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next step, more VBO, camera and lighting. Set, ready, action!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/opengl-3-2-shaders-everywhere/&quot;&gt;OpenGL 3.2: shaders everywhere!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 24, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Slowing down]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/en/slowing-down/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/en/slowing-down</id>
  <published>2011-05-25T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2011-05-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Recently all has been slowed down. The life, the earth, my environment, the
writing of my story…I feel completely stuck at the edge of a waterfall, being
dragged towards the open space ahead myself. No movements could save me from
falling away. The only thing I can really do is to prepare myself for flying
with my own wings. A wings that have never been used before. Made from wood and
heavy metal, I wonder if they will help me or ‘au contraire’ they’ll push me
down rapidly. Guess there’s only one way to know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And beneath my feet the clear water runs so free. The memories hit my back
attempting to crush me down. The ideas vanish away from my head, and the
feelings are as cold as never before. Calm down the expectations. Listen to the
white noise coming from the emptiness. Breath deeply. Open your eyes. Feel your
skin and the blood underneath. Pressure is rising. Pressure is lowering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Future? A familiar guy who I’ve never understood completely. Though I always
play his game. A game of impossibilities, bad decisions, cranky buddies and
unreachable possibilities. That’s the game. Play it or leave now. Common sense
can’t be applied. Don’t event try it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kind of english practice….kind of vital essay….&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/en/slowing-down/&quot;&gt;Slowing down&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on May 25, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[No les votes]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/no-les-votes/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/no-les-votes</id>
  <published>2011-05-19T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2011-05-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Es increíble el movimiento social que está despertando en España en estos días.
¡Estoy emocionado! Creo que por fin la gente se está empezando a dar cuenta de
que somos todos parte de la misma sociedad, ciudadanos del mismo país, al
margen de ideologías, motivaciones o gustos personales. Sin colores, sin
banderas. Solo una, la española, que es la que nos identifica a todos como
ciudadanos de este país que no está pasando por sus mejores momentos.
¿Revolución? Quizás no como las que ha habido en otros países en los últimos
meses, pero si un cambio de mentalidad importante en el pueblo español. Podemos
unirnos para intentar conseguir un bien común y mayor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todo el movimiento se puede seguir en Twitter a través de los hashtags
#acampadasol, #spanishrevolution y #nolesvotes (hay muchos más pero esos son
los más importantes, al menos para la acampada de Madrid). Yo en particular
también sigo a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.filmica.com/david_bravo/&quot;&gt;David Bravo&lt;/a&gt; (\@dbravo) abogado especialista en propiedad
intelectual y derecho informático, que ha estado presente en otros movimientos
(como las protestas contra la Ley Sinde), y que está ayudando actualmente junto
con otros colegas (Javier de la Cueva \@jdelacueva y \@bufetalmeida por ejemplo)
a que el movimiento sea posible de una manera legal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El manifiesto de #nolesvotes se puede encontrar en Google Docs &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/pub?id=139G8EL1OOR-RtfhTstHb7qekZvBoJTz1oCImbGa_I48&amp;amp;pli=1&quot;&gt;aquí&lt;/a&gt;,
aunque no se hasta cuando estará ahí colgado, así que a continuación copio y
pego los puntos importantes aparecidos en la version 2 del documento:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;nolesvotes-por-un-voto-responsable&quot;&gt;#nolesvotes: por un voto responsable&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OBJETIVO DE #NOLESVOTES. Las personas que apoyamos a la iniciativa
  #nolesvotes desde sus inicios, a la vista de la catarata de
tergiversaciones vertidas por políticos y medios de comunicación, queremos
recordar y subrayar que la iniciativa en ningún modo promueve la abstención, y
que surgió para hacer una llamada al ejercicio del voto responsable el próximo
22-M. La iniciativa pide específicamente que no se vote a los partidos que
responden a intereses distintos a los de la ciudadanía: PP, PSOE y CiU, pero
recomienda que en su lugar se examinen otras opciones. La iniciativa no pide el
voto para ninguna opción concreta: el voto es responsabilidad de cada
ciudadano.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;HAZ DE TU PÁGINA UN CARTEL ELECTORAL. Las calles están llenas de carteles
  electorales, pero muchas personas no se ven representadas en ellos: la
intermediación hizo que la política sea cada vez más lejana al ciudadano. Para
subsanar tal déficit democrático, proponemos que todo ciudadano que así lo
desee pueda convertir su blog, su web, su muro o su twitter en un &lt;strong&gt;cartel
electoral&lt;/strong&gt; del movimiento. Si quieres respaldar esta iniciativa,
convierte tu sitio en Internet en un cartel electoral antes de las 24 horas del
próximo día 20 de mayo, con el logotipo de #nolesvotes o de las plataformas con
las que simpatices, y el texto “ni PP, ni PSOE, ni CiU”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;COLABORACIÓN DISTRIBUIDA. Te invitamos a copiar este texto y construir
  páginas de enlaces que referencien todos los sitios que dan apoyo a la
iniciativa. De igual modo, invitamos a los demás colectivos que comparten
nuestra propuesta a que lleven a cabo acciones similares. La fuerza de la red
reside en la distribución y colaboración entre sus nodos.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;TÚ ERES EL ALTAVOZ. Tan importante es la red como la calle: no te limites a
  actuar en internet. Levántate y explícaselo a todos tus conocidos,
especialmente a aquellos más vulnerables a la propaganda en los medios de
comunicación masivos.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;ACCIÓN. No te quedes en casa el domingo 22. Sal a la calle y ejerce tu
  derecho al voto. No votes a quienes, actuando abiertamente en contra de la
voluntad e intereses de los ciudadanos, han convertido la democracia en una
burla de sí misma. Por la participación democrática activa: ni PP, ni PSOE, ni
CiU.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;¡TODOS A LA ACAMPADA QUE HAY EN SOL O EN CADA CIUDAD! ¡QUE SE NOS OIGA!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/no-les-votes/&quot;&gt;No les votes&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on May 19, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[A'dam]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/adam/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/adam</id>
  <published>2011-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2011-04-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Vertiginoso. No se me ocurre otro término para calificar los tres últimos meses
de mi vida.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Han ocurrido tantas cosas que me cuesta seguir la pista de mi propia historia.
Esta claro que este es un año de cambios, y me pregunto que me deparará el
futuro. Por ahora parece que algo bastante bueno, ¡así que habrá que prepararse
para disfrutarlo!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hace unas semanas viajé a Amsterdam con unos amigos para conocer la ciudad y
para visitar a mi amigo Rum que lleva allí ya tres meses viviendo. Estuvimos 4
días, y fueron los mejores cuatro días que he pasado en muchos años. Fue un
viaje mágico, lleno de encanto, cargado de esperanzas y completamente
relajante. Conocer Amsterdam, visitar sus calles, mezclarse con su gente y
disfrutar relajadamente de unos vinos a la luz del encapotado cielo Neerlandés
ha sido una experiencia inolvidable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No pensara yo que fuese a causar tal efecto sobre mí esta pequeña ciudad del
norte de Europa, pero el hecho es que me enamoré de ella, de sus canales, de
sus bicicletas y de su esencia bohemia. He quedado prendado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Después de que mucha gente me advirtiera y aconsejara que intentase relativizar
las sensaciones y sentimientos que allí experimenté, conseguí acallar el ímpetu
soñador que me había atrapado y esquivar la necesidad imperiosa de vivir de
primera mano la vida &lt;em&gt;Amsterdamer&lt;/em&gt;. Y sin embargo decidí que era el
momento perfecto para empezar a enviar curriculums a las ofertas interesantes
que fuera viendo o que me fuera enviando mi amigo Rum (¡las cuales eran ya
bastantes!). Finalmente me decidí por dos de ellas, las cuales envié entre la
semana pasada y esta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pues hete aquí que me hallaba tranquilamente sumergido en mis cotidianidades
laborales, médicas y gimnásticas cuando de repente han contactado conmigo de
las dos ofertas ¡¡¡¡¡¡Ñiiiiiicccc!!!!!!!! Era como ir sin frenos, cuesta abajo,
y con el acelerador pisado. Fue muy interesante porque de una de ellas me
llamaron por teléfono y así pude practicar un poco mi inglés. Creo que no se me
dio mal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En definitiva, una de las ofertas era para trabajar de forma temporal en
Amsterdam durante 6 meses para luego pasar a trabajar en UK. Les comenté que no
me interesaba. Que prefería poder quedarme en Amsterdam más tiempo, así que
estoy a la espera de que me confirmen si habría posibilidad de quedarse más
tiempo en ese puesto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La otra oferta es para RIPE NCC, en el mismo centro de Amsterdam. Tiene muy
buena pinta y he concertado una entrevista presencial con ellos allí en
Amsterdam para el 4 de Mayo. Viendo que me han llamado enseguida, que ya
conocen mis expectativas salariales y que me van a pagar el viaje hasta allí,
creo que hay bastante interés, aunque no se si significa mucho o no. Pero
bueno, intentaré hacerlo lo mejor que pueda ¡y a ver si hay suerte!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¿De los nervios? Si. ¿Contento? También. Además justo después de la entrevista
en Amsterdam me quedo unos días allí para disfrutar de la estancia con mi amigo
y luego me voy a París de viaje de placer. ¡¿Que más se puede pedir?! Lo único
&lt;em&gt;negativo&lt;/em&gt; es que no se si podré hacer el examen del FCE, que el
seguro del coche se extendía hasta septiembre, que tengo que vender el vehículo
y que el contrato con Movistar dura hasta mediados del año que viene. En fin,
¡nimiedades comparadas con lo que de verdad importa!.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tiempos de cambios, nuevos retos, futuros inciertos y muchas ganas de vivirlo
todo al máximo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En fin, una vez que esté allí, invitados quedáis a visitarme.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/adam/&quot;&gt;A&#39;dam&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on April 13, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pasión y realidad]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/pasion-y-realidad/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/pasion-y-realidad</id>
  <published>2011-03-09T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2011-03-09T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Recientemente he sabido de dos perlas relacionadas con el mundo de los
videojuegos que ya me están haciendo salivar y anhelar que el tiempo pase más
rápido para llegar cuanto antes a finales de década. Recientemente se ha
celebrado la &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gdconf.com/&quot;&gt;Game Developer Conference&lt;/a&gt; en San Francisco, California, y
aparte de todas las novedades en videojuegos que cabía esperar (y manidos
remakes de antaño), ha aparecido &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epicgames.com/&quot;&gt;Epic Games&lt;/a&gt; con su maravillosísimo &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unrealengine.com/&quot;&gt;Unreal
Engine&lt;/a&gt; y su visión de cómo serán los juegos dentro de unos
años…gracias por supuesto a su motor líder en ventas. Verdaderas joyas
como &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bioshockgame.com/&quot;&gt;BioShock&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://masseffect.bioware.com/&quot;&gt;Mass Effect&lt;/a&gt; o el exitoso &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epicgames.com/infinityblade/&quot;&gt;Infinity Blade&lt;/a&gt; (al que
por cierto estoy últimamente muy enganchado), son solo muestras de la potencia
de este motor en su versión actual para Next Gen y para portátiles/móviles
(como la versión del motor &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.udk.com/&quot;&gt;UDK&lt;/a&gt; para dispositivos como iPhone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En la GDC Epic ha echado una mirada al futuro de los videojuegos a través del
bisel de su propio motor, y la verdad que el resultado es (teniendo en cuenta
que es una prueba de concepto) impresionante. Si dentro de 3 o 4 años los
videojuegos se parecen a lo que se muestra en &lt;a href=&quot;http://uk.ign.com/videos/2011/03/08/see-the-next-generation-of-video-games-in-action&quot;&gt;este video&lt;/a&gt; me voy a hacer
directamente acólito del Sagrado Motor de Videojuegos. El nivel de realismo me
parece apabullante, los detalles, las luces, las sombras. Es curioso a lo que
nos hemos acostumbrado los jugadores habituales de videojuegos (hardcore
gamers), porque aunque me parece absolutamente delicioso el trailer de casi 3
minutos, y creo que la experiencia de juego sería increiblemente vívida, aún
falta para alcanzar el fotorealismo…pero estamos en el camino.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solo hay que echar la vista atrás y darse cuenta de lo que ha ocurrido en la
última década con los videojuegos. El avance ha sido…exponencial. Y si
sigue así yo creo que a finales de década estaremos cerca del fotorrealismo en
videojuegos. Supongo que en ese momento los llamaremos Augmented Movies, First
Person Movies o Immersion Movies, a saber, y me encantará poder estar allí
cuando ocurra para disfrutar de ello.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Como guinda final, otra perla de la que he sido consciente hace más bien poco:
el nuevo juego de &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rockstargames.com/&quot;&gt;Rockstar Games&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rockstargames.com/lanoire/&quot;&gt;L.A. Noire&lt;/a&gt;, una historia de cine
negro muy cuidada y con bastante estilo. El gameplay parece bastante similar a
Grand Theft Auto, aunque salvando las distancias. Los gráficos tienen más
estilo y la temática es completamente distinta. Sin embargo hay algo que me ha
llamado gratamente la atención, y es la nueva tecnología de reconocimiento
facial que han desarrollado para el juego, y que permite incluir hasta el más
mínimo detalle de la interpretación de los actores en el videojuego. Viendo el
video, la sensación es un poco extraña: entre &lt;em&gt;¡Wow, parecen personas de
verdad!&lt;/em&gt; y &lt;em&gt;Mmmm, aunque en realidad se nota que son
muñecos&lt;/em&gt;. Partiendo de que es la primera vez que se hace esto y que ya
llegarán versiones mejoradas de la misma tecnología, me parece que estamos ante
una técnica revolucionara que cambiará la manera en la que vemos los
videojuegos a medio plazo: ¡ya estoy viendo nuevas estrellas surgidas
directamente de los píxeles de la pantalla!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El video de L.A. Noire &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/rockstargames#p/a/u/1/q2EG5J05048&quot;&gt;aquí&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/pasion-y-realidad/&quot;&gt;Pasión y realidad&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on March 09, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Llévame a la luna]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/llevame-a-la-luna/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/llevame-a-la-luna</id>
  <published>2011-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2011-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;¡Calentando motores y preparando el despegue! Últimamente ando configurando mi
vida (si, configurando, como si fuera un ordenador) para preparar mi particular
vuelo hacia la luna. Concienciándome para apartarme de la relajante
cotidianeidad de mi vida y emprender un pequeño viaje a la periferia de mi
mundo. No tan difícil. No tan fácil. Siempre parece haber etapas. A mi me ha
tocado vivir de nuevo un fin de etapa y un nuevo comienzo. Quizás sea la edad,
pero simplemente me parece &lt;em&gt;correcto&lt;/em&gt;, como diría un gran amigo
mío. ¿Me gusta? ¿Es peor? ¿Quizás sea necesario? Ya no lo se, ni me importa
realmente. No me malinterpretéis: no estoy enfadado con la vida ni nada por el
estilo. En realidad casi estoy agradecido por la oportunidad de poder cambiar.
Y no solo por este último cambio. En general, por todos los cambios que
vinieron y por los que vendrán. Simplemente porque me dan la oportunidad de
probarme a mi mismo: probar mi voluntad, mi desidia, mi ánimo y desánimo, mi
fortaleza, mi mente y mi cuerpo. Y por ahora me gusto, estoy contento con cómo
soy. No al cien por cien, por supuesto, pero si en un alto grado y teniendo en
cuenta la edad que tengo. Ya habrá más cuando sea mayor…y menos,
obviamente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mis clases de inglés, mi entrenamiento de gimnasio, mi trabajo con
decodificadores y C++, mi pequeño repunte musical, el inevitable escarceo hacia
un país extranjero, incluso hasta quizás algo de teatro son las cosas que
ocupan mi mente hoy por hoy. Disfrutar y aprender: ¿qué más podría pedir?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mmmmm, un poco más de salud, que últimamente mis achaques óseos y musculares me
están dando un poco por donde Gollum perdió el anillo. Nada que no solucione un
poco de ejercicio, un poco de Ibuprofeno y alguna visita esporádica al médico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoy: Ensalada para comer, ejercicio de espalda en el gym, 20 minutos
corriendo…&lt;em&gt;and english classes to end the day&lt;/em&gt;. ¡A disfrutar
del menu!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/llevame-a-la-luna/&quot;&gt;Llévame a la luna&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on March 01, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meme]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/meme/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/meme</id>
  <published>2011-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2011-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;Ayer me llegó a través de facebook un nuevo meme que se está extendiendo por
esta red social. El meme reza lo siguiente:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Entra en la wikipedia y dale a “Página Aleatoria”.  El título del primer
artículo es el nombre de tu Grupo de música.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ve a la página Quotationspage.com y dale al botón “Random Quotes”.  Las
últimas cuatro o cinco palabras de la última cita de esa página es el tíulo de
tu primer álbum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ve a Flickr y dale al botón “Explorar últimos 7 días”.  La tercera imagen
que aparezca será la portada de tu álbum.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Usa un editor para ponerlo todo junto (photoshop, gimp..).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Súbelo con este texto en la anotación y etiqueta a tus colegas.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Normalmente no me adhiero a estas campañas, pero esta me hizo gracia y terminé
haciendo la portada de mi disco. ¡Aquí tenéis el resultado!:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/images/ianblack.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ian Black&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/meme/&quot;&gt;Meme&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 20, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diferentes etapas]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/diferentes-etapas/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/diferentes-etapas</id>
  <published>2011-02-19T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2011-02-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Veinticinco balas malgastadas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Apunté hacia el cielo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;y conseguí matar a un dios&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Veinticinco almas devastadas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;y no he conseguido ser yo&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cariño, he venido a decirte&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;que he perdido el sentido&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;No te asustes si no sientes mi latir&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mi prisión se ha vuelto espesa&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Me atraganta y me indaga&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ninguna otra me conoce mejor&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Veinticinco dagas bien clavadas&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;en un mismo corazón&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ahógame entre tus brazos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Y ámame&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ayúdame a controlar la ansiedad&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Discúlpame si no he de cambiar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Solo otra bala más…&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;¿Para qué son&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;si no son para matar?&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mi alma probó el sabor de la pólvora&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;pero el dulce aroma a victoria&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;nunca más caerá en mis manos&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ahora solo me quedan tus labios&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;y el susurro de alguna canción&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/diferentes-etapas/&quot;&gt;Diferentes etapas&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 19, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Canciones de una vida ajetreada]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/canciones-de-una-vida-ajetreada/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/canciones-de-una-vida-ajetreada</id>
  <published>2011-02-15T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2011-02-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;He decidido añadir una nueva sección a este renovado blog. Una sección que
habla de mi vida de una manera un tanto diferente. Habla de lo que fui y de lo
que soy y, sobre todo, de como he llegado a ser el de hoy. La sección se llama
&lt;strong&gt;Poesías cantadas&lt;/strong&gt; y es una recopilación de canciones que escribía
hace algunos años. A fecha de hoy no están todas las que conservo, pero aún no
las he encontrado todas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El objetivo principal es no perder esas letras. El secundario recordar lo que
fui y entender mejor el camino que he recorrido hasta el presente. Y el
terciario intentar presionarme para plasmar esas letras como canción de una vez
por todas. Los dos primeros ya están cubiertos. Veremos cuanto tardo en cumplir
el tercero. Mientras tanto tendré que seguir escarbando entre papeles añejos
para encontrar el resto de poesías cantadas.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/canciones-de-una-vida-ajetreada/&quot;&gt;Canciones de una vida ajetreada&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 15, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>


  

<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revolución]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://www.robertocano.es/es/revolucion/" />
  <id>http://www.robertocano.es/es/revolucion</id>
  <published>2011-02-13T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2011-02-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name></name>
    <uri>http://www.robertocano.es</uri>
    
  </author>
  <content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;De la rabia entre mis manos hablo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Con ira entiendo las cuerdas que me atan, esclavo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Quiero surgir de entre ahogos inhumanos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;No puedo…de la rabia entre mis manos hablo&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;De la importancia ante mi alma callo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Sugiero tranquilos escarceos&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;La mano que miente me duele y me tiene&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Y cedo…por la impotencia ante mi alma muero&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Escudriño internos sentimientos de revuelo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Rebelión sobre el infierno eterno&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Del que vive por muerte en su propio cementerio&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No estoy preparado para aunar mi libertad&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Y gritar con fuerza: ¡Basta ya!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Bastará un ahogo más&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Entiendo peones en rededor&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;que bailan cada uno a su son&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;a un ritmo frenético que no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;pertecene a mi fuero interior&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;La red se estrecha&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;¡A mí legión!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;No deseo&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;ser otro&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;peón&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Ya no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Yo no&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;No, porque soy el que mece las palabras en mi propia conclusión&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Y he decidido que más que vivir por estar&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;quiero estar para vivir&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Y es así como quiero seguir&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;De la rabia entre mis manos callo&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es/es/revolucion/&quot;&gt;Revolución&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Roberto Cano at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robertocano.es&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on February 13, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

  </content>
</entry>

</feed>
